Guide to the Kerby Miller Papers AIA.076
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kerby Miller Papers
1958-2013
1989-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Miller, Kerby A.
AIA.076
11.3 Linear Feet in 23 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box
Kerby A. Miller is an historian and Curators' Professor at the University of Missouri. His teaching and published work focuses on Irish history, often with an emphasis on social, immigration, and urban history. The Kerby Miller Papers date between 1958 and 2013, with the bulk of the material dating between 1989 and 2003. The collection consists of materials created or collected by Miller in the course of his research, teaching, and writing on Irish and Irish American history. Materials include photocopies of American Loyalists' petitions to the British government, a run of British Information Services news bulletins concerning the conflict in Northern Ireland, and research materials created in the course of his academic scholarship, including original writings, reviews of his work, photocopied letters from Irish immigrants and citizens, and correspondence between Miller and other academics and institutions. Major subjects and themes present in these research files include pre- and post-immigration economic issues, experiences coming to and first impressions of living in America, genealogical records, and accounts of Irish family life.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kerby Miller in April and June 2015. The accession number associated with this gift is 2015.018 and 2015.051.
Related Archival Materials
Archives of Irish America Irish Republicanism Papers (AIA 022)
Frank Durkan Papers (AIA 008)
Bruce Boling Papers (AIA 062)
Paul O'Dwyer Papers (AIA 069)
Biographical Note
Kerby A. Miller is a historian and Curators' Professor at the University of Missouri. Miller graduated from Pomona College in 1966 and the University of California, Berkley with an M.A. in 1967 and a Ph.D in 1976. His teaching and published work often focus on Irish and Irish American history, with an emphasis on social, immigration, and urban issues. During his career, Miller has served as an adviser, consultant, and visiting professor for many institutions. He has authored or co-authored numerous books, journal articles, and essays, including Emigrants and Exiles: Ireland and the Irish Exodus to North America; Out of Ireland: The Story of Irish Emigration to America; Irish Immigrants in the Land of Canaan: Letters and Memoirs from Colonial and Revolutionary America, 1675-1815; and Ireland and Irish America: Culture, Class, and Transatlantic Migration.
Scope and Content Note
The Kerby Miller Papers consist of materials created or collected by Miller in the course of his research, teaching, and writing on Irish and Irish American history. The collection dates from 1958 to 2013, with the bulk of material between 1989 and 2003. The bulk of the collection consists of Miller's research files which include photocopies of material dating from the 17th through the 19th centuries, Miller's extensive notes on this material, his notes on relevant books and articles, and correspondence regarding his research. Miller's correspondents include historians, archivists, and librarians in the United States, United Kingdom, and Ireland, with historian Bruce Boling being the most frequent correspondent. Major subjects and themes present in these research files include accounts of Irish family life, pre- and post-immigration economic issues, and experiences coming to and first impressions of living in America.
Other material in the collection includes photocopies of American Loyalists' petitions to the British government during the American Revolutionary War asking for compensation for losses, explaining their political acts and affiliations, and describing their lives in America; a run of British Information Services news bulletins on various aspects of the conflict in Northern Ireland during the late 1980s and early 1990s; and reviews of Miller's work. Subjects that frequently appear in the British Information Services bulletins include religion, electoral politics, employment discrimination, paramilitary funerals, law enforcement practices or regulations, and incidents of violence attributed to various Irish republican paramilitary groups. Also included are dossiers of republican organizations including Sinn Fein, the Official Irish Republican Army (IRA), the Provisional Irish Republican Army (IRA or PIRA), and the Irish National Liberation Army (INLA). Also present are excerpts of statements made by officials or other prominent figures.
Great Britain -- History -- 20th century.; Ireland -- History -- 18th century.; Ireland -- Emigration and immigration.; American loyalists.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Northern Ireland -- History -- 1969-1994.; Irish Americans -- History.; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; United States -- History -- 1783-1865.; Research (document genres).; Correspondence.; British Information Services
- American Loyalist Petitions to the British Government, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1-19, Box 2, Folder 1-11, Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  Existence and Location of Originals
  Photocopies of this material was made from a microfilm collection entitled "American Loyalists: Transcripts of the Manuscript Books and Papers of the Commission of Inquiry into the Losses and Services of the American Loyalists" that was transcribed for the New York Public Library. The original records from which the microfilm collection was created are housed in the Public Record Office of England.
- British Information Services bulletins, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6-11, Box 4, Folder 1-9, Box 5, Folder 1)
- Nolan, Nicholas. "A Celtic Exodus, or the Irish Emigration", 1933, Undated (Box 24, Folder 13, Box Shared Tamiment 003, Folder 14-16)
- Rev. Samuel Blair, 1996-2002 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
- Memoir (probably from journal notes) -- Rev. John Craig, 1996-2001 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
- Rev. John Craig, 1990-1996 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
- Mary Cummings, 1989-1995 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
- Margaret Carey Murphy Burke, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 10, Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- McAleer research -- Margaret Carey, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Thomas Shipboy, 1990-1992 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
- Shipboy letters, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Reviews -- Field Day book, 2009-2012 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Reviews -- Emigrants and Exiles, 1985-2010 (Box 6, Folder 8-9, Box 7, Folder 1)
- Reviews -- Irish Immigrants in the Land of Canaan, 2000-2010 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
- Reviews -- Miscellaneous essays, 2000-2013 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Reviews -- Coffee-table books, 1994-2001 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Reviews -- Pop Culture, 1998-2005 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Journalism on Kerby Miller, 1986-2008 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Films and film reviews, 1986-2000 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
- San Patricios film, 1996-2007 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous ephemera and letters, 1985-1999 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Bernard M'Kenna, 1996-2000 (Box 7, Folder 12-13, Box 8, Folder 1-3, Box 24, Folder 1)
- David Lindsey, 1989-1999 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
- Johnstone (From Ireland) letters, 1773-1808, 1988-1999 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Moses Johnston research materials, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
- Devereux Family letters, 1798-1800, 1990-1995 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- John Devereaux, 1958, 1990-1995 (Box 8, Folder 10, Box 9, Folder 1)
- McNish/Kerr letters, 1806-1820, 1989-1997 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
- Alexander McNish research materials, 1989-1990 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
- Anonymous Ulster poet (In Irish), 18th century, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Rev. James McSparron, 1996-2009 (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
- Robert Parke, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 10-12)
- Chester County Quaker Meeting House photograph, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
- John Rea, 1989-1999 (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
- Dunlop letters, 1785-1811, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- John Dunlop, Undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
- John Smilie letter, 1762, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- John Smylie, voyage letter, 1762; and John Huey, voyage letter, 1773, Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
- John O'Raw, 1989-1999 (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
- B.8. Thomas Hinds, 1795, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Shepherd/Wansborough, 1700-1741, 1988-1999 (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
- Thomas Shepherd, 1990-1999 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Scottish tenant's letter, 1710s-1730s, 1988-1997 (Box 10, Folder 15-16)
- Londonberry, N.H. petitions, 1720-1730, 1997-2001 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Dr. Charles Carroll, 1748, 1995-2002 (Box 10, Folder 18, Box 11, Folder 1)
- Charles Lewis Reily letter, 1749, 1995-2000 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
- Samuel Bryan letter, 1752, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Rev. Thomas Barton, 1995-1997 (Box 11, Folder 5-11)
- Thomas Burke, 1990-1998 (Box 11, Folder 12, Box 12, Folder 1-3)
- Rev. Francis Alison, 1760s-1770s, 1990-2006 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
- Rev. Francis Alison (letters, 1767-1772) Philadelphia and Rev. Gilbert Tennent (November 1741) Pennsylvania, 1990-1997 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
- Morton, 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 8-9, Box 21, Folder 10, Box 22, Folder 1)
- Greer Family letters, 1764-1808, 1988-1996 (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
- Thomas Wright, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- James McCullough, 1993-1995 (Box 13, Folder 2-7, Box 14, Folder 12-13, Box 24, Folder 6)
- Elizabeth Brownlee petition, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 8-10, Box 14, Folder 1)
- Daniel Kent letters, 1785-1794, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Kent memoir, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 3-5)
- John and Jane Chambers, 1989-2000 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
- Wright Family letters, 1801-1860s, 1988-2008 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
- Joseph Wright research materials, 1988-1990 (Box 14, Folder 10-11, Box 24, Folder 7)
- Edward Toner letters, 1818-1819, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1, Box 24, Folder 5)
- Edward and Mary Toner, 1815-1844, 1990-2000 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
- Crockett Family, 1989-2001 (Box 15, Folder 4-10)
- Blake Family letters, 1987-1999 (Box 15, Folder 11-12, Box 16, Folder 1-2)
- Maine Scots-Irish petition, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Robert Witherspoon, 1985-2000 (Box 16, Folder 4-6)
- Mary Greenlee deposition, 1730s, 1993-2001 (Box 16, Folder 7, Box 17, Folder 6-7)
- Matthew Carey, 1990-2000 (Box 16, Folder 8-9, Box 17, Folder 1-2, Box 20, Folder 1-3, Box 23, Folder 11, Box 24, Folder 8-10)
- James Magraw letter, 1733, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 3-5)
- 1799 St. Mary's Church riot, Philadelphia, Undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Fr. Patrick Kenny diary, 1790s-1820s, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 9-10)
- Mac Arthur letters, 1997-1999 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
- John Nevin, 1988-2006 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
- Emmet (Simms letter 2 November 1807), 1990-1997 (Box 18, Folder 7-8)
- William Heazelton, 1989-1996 (Box 18, Folder 9-11)
- John Caldwell, 1989-2002 (Box 18, Folder 12-13, Box 19, Folder 1-3)
- Chester County petitions, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 4-5)
- More servants and laborers, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
- Irish criminals' memoirs, 1765, 1991-2002 (Box 19, Folder 8-9)
- James Patton memoir, 1839, Undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Brown Family letters, 1793-1816, Undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Samuel Brown, James Brown, and Thomas Brown, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Brown, Revisions, Philadelphia strikes, etc, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
- Francis Campbell, 1995-1996 (Box 20, Folder 8-9)
- Robert Pillson, 1989-2000 (Box 20, Folder 10-12)
- John O'Kelly, 1773, 1978, 1995-1996 (Box 21, Folder 1-3, Box 24, Folder 11)
- Redic-Burke (and Findlay, Bryan, etc.), 1997 (Box 21, Folder 4-5, Box 24, Folder 2)
- John Kennedy petition, 1753, 1995-2002 (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Benjamin Chandlee letters, 1705-1707, 1996-1998 (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Chester County, Pennsylvania servants' petitions, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 8)
- John McDonnell, 1996-1998 (Box 21, Folder 9, Box 23, Folder 6-7)
- Caldwell Family letters, 1774, 1996-1997 (Box 22, Folder 2-3)
- James Caldwell research materials, 1989-1996 (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Matthew Patten diary, 1996-1997 (Box 22, Folder 5-8)
- South Carolina Loyalists' petitions, 1996-2000 (Box 22, Folder 9)
- Loyalists' petitions (and Crary article), 1994 (Box 22, Folder 10-11)
- Job Johnston, 1989-1990 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
- Reddick-Burke letters, 1787-1788, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 3-4)
- Post-Revolution politics, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 5)
- McCurtin, 1992-2000 (Box 23, Folder 8-10)
- Photocopies from the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)